<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-11T15:58:27+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leo Alcock</title><subtitle>Personal site for Leo C Alcock. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Yet another thing about the golden ratio Part I</title><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/elementary-pisot-i/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yet another thing about the golden ratio Part I"/><published>2025-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/elementary-pisot-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/elementary-pisot-i/"><![CDATA[<p>Awhile back I saw a list of “almost integers” - numbers which <em>coincidentally</em> are almost integral. It started by noting that the powers of the golden ratio, $\varphi = \frac{1 + \sqrt{5}}{2}$, get closer and closer to being integral:</p> \[\begin{align*} \varphi^{1} &amp;\approx 1.6180339887499\\ \varphi^{2} &amp;\approx 2.6180339887499\\ \varphi^{3} &amp;\approx 4.2360679774998\\ \varphi^{5} &amp;\approx 11.090169943749\\ \varphi^{8} &amp;\approx 46.978713763748\\ \varphi^{13} &amp;\approx 521.00191937873\\ \varphi^{21} &amp;\approx 24476.000040856\\ \varphi^{22} &amp;\approx 39602.999974749 \end{align*}\] <p>You might also notice that the odd powers are a little above an integer and the even powers are a little below an integer. Now, knowing a little algebraic number theory you can immediately see why this is. Let $\bar{\varphi} = \frac{1 - \sqrt{5}}{2} = -\frac{1}{\varphi} \approx -0.61803$, then one has \begin{equation} \varphi^n + {\bar{\varphi}}^n \in \mathbb{Z} \end{equation} is always an integer. Given this fact, one notices that the term $\bar{\varphi}^n$ approaches $0$ exponentially and alternates between being negative and positive. Thus we have that \begin{equation} \varphi^n = l_n - \left(-\frac{1}{\varphi}\right)^n, l_n\in \mathbb{Z} \end{equation}</p> <p><strong>Lemma</strong> Given a monic, irreducible, integer polynomial, $f(x) = x^n + a_{n-1}x^{n-1}+\cdots + a_0, a_i\in \mathbb{Z}$ the sum of $k$th powers of its roots is always an integer.</p> <p>Roots of polynomials of this form are called <em>algebraic integers</em>. Examples include, $\varphi, \sqrt{2}, \mathbb{Z}, r = \sqrt[3]{19}, i, \frac{1 + r + r^2}{3}$, but not numbers like $\frac{1}{2}, \pi, e, \frac{1 + r + r^2}{6}$. Every algebraic integer has a unique <em>minimal polynomial</em>, the lowest degree monic polynomial which has it as a root. For $\sqrt[n]{d}$, its $x^n - d$, for $\varphi$, $x^2 - x -1$, and for $\frac{1+r+r^2}{3}$, its $x^3- x^2-6x-12$. The other roots of an algebraic integer’s minimal polynomial are called <em>conjugates</em>. $\sqrt{2}$’s unique conjugate is $-\sqrt{2}$, and $\varphi$’s unique conjugate is $-1/\varphi$. One might notice</p> \[\varphi = \frac{1+\sqrt{5}}{2}, \bar{\varphi} = \frac{1-\sqrt{5}}{2}\] <p>If this reminds you of complex conjugation, you are on the right track. In fact, $a+ib, a,b\in \mathbb{Z}$ are algebraic integers and their conjugates are $a - ib$ respectively. Similar to complex conjugation, “conjugation”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> respects addition and multiplication: $\overline{a+b} = \bar{a}+\bar{b}, \overline{ab} = \bar{a}\bar{b}$. And, just as $z+\bar{z} \in \mathbb{R}$, the sum of all conjugates of an algebraic integer is integral.</p> <p>This last fact is what proves the above lemma and immediately see that $\varphi^n$ gets closer and closer to being integral. We know now that $\varphi^n + \bar{\varphi}^n$ is integral, and since $|\bar{\varphi}|&lt;1$ it contributes exponentially little to the sum over time. However, if you compute the numbers $l_n = \varphi^n + \bar{\varphi}^n$, you may see a familiar pattern:</p> \[l_n: 2, 1, 3, 4, 7, 11, 18, 29, 47,\ldots\] <p>You see that the sums of powers follow a very simple, and familiar, recurrence relation: $l_n = l_{n-1} + l_{n-2}$. This suggests that there may be another proof that $\varphi^n$ becomes more integral over time that doesn’t use any algebraic number theory at all. If one proves that this recurrence relation holds, and that the solution to the recurrence is $l_n = \varphi^n + \bar{\varphi}^n$, then computing $l_0 = 2, l_1 = 1$ proves that every subsequent $l_n$ is integral. In Part II, I’ll prove this fact in an “elementary” way. It won’t use any knowledge past single variable calculus (though having seen a generating function before would help).</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>For the technical, action by an element of $\text{Gal}(\bar{\mathbb{Q}}/\mathbb{Q})$ on an algebraic integer in $\bar{\mathbb{Q}}$. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="elementary-math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Awhile back I saw a list of “almost integers” - numbers which coincidentally are almost integral. It started by noting that the powers of the golden ratio, $\varphi = \frac{1 + \sqrt{5}}{2}$, get closer and closer to being integral:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding physics with no math background</title><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding physics with no math background"/><published>2025-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning/"><![CDATA[<p>A year or so back, someone asked a question on a public forum about how to learn quantum mechanics when coming from non-technical background. She felt that a lot of the texts out there weren’t very credible and that the rigorous texts were often too dense to get through.</p> <p>I wrote a comment giving my two cents about how the layman should learn physics, mathematics, or other similarly technical fields. It got a very positive response so I have lightly edited it here and added another tip to round things off.</p> <blockquote> <p>I’m so interested in quantum physics but it’s such a struggle for me to find credible sources on it! A lot of the people who discuss it from a spiritual standpoint feel a little bit dishonest to me, like they’re stretching scientific findings to make conclusions that actual quantum physicists would never make. Do you recommend any books/speakers on this topic who you trust?</p> </blockquote> <p>I can’t really speak to the spiritual side of things - but as a mathematician interested in science communication, I do have a lot of thoughts on public understanding of abstract things from physics and math.</p> <p><em>TL;DR for physics: Look into Feynmann’s public-facing works.</em></p> <p>Knowing the mathematics, I know that if you have a strong understanding of the math you can truly understand these non-intuitive phenomena and theories. Mathematics is an objective language that was created to discuss scientific phenomena. We needed an objective language because human intuition doesn’t always map onto the science well. So, one option is to try to delve deep into the physics/math. But honestly, if you don’t already know a lot mathematics or physics, that seems like too much work to ask of you.</p> <p>SO, what can be done in that case? Well, I’m not convinced that you <em>can’t</em> have a meaningful understanding of quantum mechanics, relativity, all these other physics things without knowing the mathematics. Although I have not come across any writing by someone without these qualifications that gave a fully correct summarization. Even experts in related fields get these things wrong… Michio Kaku’s latest book on quantum computing is riddled with basic errors… In sum, my general advice is this:</p> <h3 id="5-step-guide-to-understanding-technical-things-mathphysicsetc-for-the-layman">5 Step guide to understanding technical things (math/physics/etc) for the layman</h3> <p><strong>1. Make sure the authors behind whatever source you’re learning from have the requisite technical background.</strong></p> <p>As mentioned before, even the best science communicators will get a number of details, and even often general themes, wrong. These areas are difficult! Similarly, even scientists or academics in adjacent fields can overestimate their understanding of a given field. Try your best to find a writer close with a relevant background in the field.</p> <p>For physics, I would start by watching/reading Feynmann’s public facing works. He was a great science communicator and had an intuition for the physics better than literally everyone in the world in his time.</p> <p><strong>2. While learning, ask yourself “What would it mean if this is not true?” and “What does this mean in a physical way?”</strong></p> <p>Due to great abstraction, you’ll find no shortage of metaphor in reading about physics. Waves, particles, fields… all of these are in a sense abstractions. Wave-particle duality and all that. What could “Time moves at different speeds in different reference frames.” even mean? A speed is relative to time, so… are there different times moving different relative to other times? Is there an example showing what this means in terms of something I, myself, could observe and what would it be like if the universe didn’t work like that?</p> <p><a href="https://youtu.be/lZ3bPUKo5zc?si=_xKPNol-3kSkobit">This lecture</a> gives a great intuitive discussion on what do we mean by “wave-particle duality.” If I were to reframe its central point in a few sentences. I’d say, calling the quantum phenomena “wave-particle duality” is kind of like calling a cylinder a type of “cube-sphere duality.” Thinking of a cylinder as some cube-sphere hybrid is a little odd, even if it makes some sense. Really, it is its own thing different from a cube or a sphere. Though cylinders are hard to picture if you have only grown up with cubes and spheres.</p> <p><strong>3. If you can, ask your local nerd. Be humble, and don’t worry about getting details wrong.</strong></p> <p>I have a confession to make: I’m a nerd. I’m also a nerd who knows lots of other nerds and I can confidently say we love spinning yarns about this shit. See the above writing…</p> <p><strong>4. It is ok if you don’t get it the first time, or the second, or the third, or the fo…</strong></p> <p>The dirty little secret is that oftentimes the experts don’t get a lot of it too. There are many many things that I’ve seen many many times that I don’t fully get. I feel like I’m just starting to get probability theory. And either way, declaring to yourself that you fully understand something is really a bit somber. You’ve sealed yourself off from further exploration and decided that you have had enough. I respect those who say “I don’t understand this” after a lot of experience with something much more than those who confidently say they do understand it.</p> <p><strong>5. Continue to be open and curious even when it seems daunting or you feel out of your depth.</strong></p> <p>Truthfully, I think every field’s details contain nuance that can seem impassable - just in physics (or mathematics etc), that wall is more visible. It is easier to tell that there is a lot you might not be getting. I’d say, explore anyway. Explore broadly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-education"/><category term="expository"/><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Five simple tips for the layman who wants to understand mathematics, physics, or similarly technical fields.]]></summary></entry></feed>