<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-10T13:26:20+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leo Alcock</title><subtitle>Personal site for Leo C Alcock. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Understanding Physics with No Math Background</title><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Physics with No Math Background"/><published>2025-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/layman-learning/"><![CDATA[<p>A year or so back, someone asked a question on a public forum about how to learn quantum mechanics when coming from non-technical background. She felt that a lot of the texts out there weren’t very credible and that the rigorous texts were often too dense to get through.</p> <p>I wrote a comment giving my two cents about how the layman should learn physics, mathematics, or other similarly technical fields. It got a very positive response so I have lightly edited it here and added another tip to round things off.</p> <blockquote> <p>I’m so interested in quantum physics but it’s such a struggle for me to find credible sources on it! A lot of the people who discuss it from a spiritual standpoint feel a little bit dishonest to me, like they’re stretching scientific findings to make conclusions that actual quantum physicists would never make. Do you recommend any books/speakers on this topic who you trust?</p> </blockquote> <p>I can’t really speak to the spiritual side of things - but as a mathematician interested in science communication, I do have a lot of thoughts on public understanding of abstract things from physics and math.</p> <p><em>TL;DR for physics: Look into Feynmann’s public-facing works.</em></p> <p>Knowing the mathematics, I know that if you have a strong understanding of the math you can truly understand these non-intuitive phenomena and theories. Mathematics is an objective language that was created to discuss scientific phenomena. We needed an objective language because human intuition doesn’t always map onto the science well. So, one option is to try to delve deep into the physics/math. But honestly, if you don’t already know a lot mathematics or physics, that seems like too much work to ask of you.</p> <p>SO, what can be done in that case? Well, I’m not convinced that you <em>can’t</em> have a meaningful understanding of quantum mechanics, relativity, all these other physics things without knowing the mathematics. Although I have not come across any writing by someone without these qualifications that gave a fully correct summarization. Even experts in related fields get these things wrong… Michio Kaku’s latest book on quantum computing is riddled with basic errors… In sum, my general advice is this:</p> <h3 id="5-step-guide-to-understanding-technical-things-mathphysicsetc-for-the-layman">5 Step guide to understanding technical things (math/physics/etc) for the layman</h3> <p><strong>1. Make sure the authors behind whatever source you’re learning from have the requisite technical background.</strong></p> <p>As mentioned before, even the best science communicators will get a number of details, and even often general themes, wrong. These areas are difficult! Similarly, even scientists or academics in adjacent fields can overestimate their understanding of a given field. Try your best to find a writer close with a relevant background in the field.</p> <p>For physics, I would start by watching/reading Feynmann’s public facing works. He was a great science communicator and had an intuition for the physics better than literally everyone in the world in his time.</p> <p><strong>2. While learning, ask yourself “What would it mean if this is not true?” and “What does this mean in a physical way?”</strong></p> <p>Due to great abstraction, you’ll find no shortage of metaphor in reading about physics. Waves, particles, fields… all of these are in a sense abstractions. Wave-particle duality and all that. What could “Time moves at different speeds in different reference frames.” even mean? A speed is relative to time, so… are there different times moving different relative to other times? Is there an example showing what this means in terms of something I, myself, could observe and what would it be like if the universe didn’t work like that?</p> <p><a href="https://youtu.be/lZ3bPUKo5zc?si=_xKPNol-3kSkobit">This lecture</a> gives a great intuitive discussion on what do we mean by “wave-particle duality.” If I were to reframe its central point in a few sentences. I’d say, calling the quantum phenomena “wave-particle duality” is kind of like calling a cylinder a type of “cube-sphere duality.” Thinking of a cylinder as some cube-sphere hybrid is a little odd, even if it makes some sense. Really, it is its own thing different from a cube or a sphere. Though cylinders are hard to picture if you have only grown up with cubes and spheres.</p> <p><strong>3. If you can, ask your local nerd. Be humble, and don’t worry about getting details wrong.</strong></p> <p>I have a confession to make: I’m a nerd. I’m also a nerd who knows lots of other nerds and I can confidently say we love spinning yarns about this shit. See the above writing…</p> <p><strong>4. It is ok if you don’t get it the first time, or the second, or the third, or the fo…</strong></p> <p>The dirty little secret is that oftentimes the experts don’t get a lot of it too. There are many many things that I’ve seen many many times that I don’t fully get. I feel like I’m just starting to get probability theory. And either way, declaring to yourself that you fully understand something is really a bit somber. You’ve sealed yourself off from further exploration and decided that you have had enough. I respect those who say “I don’t understand this” after a lot of experience with something much more than those who confidently say they do understand it.</p> <p><strong>5. Continue to be open and curious even when it seems daunting or you feel out of your depth.</strong></p> <p>Truthfully, I think every field’s details contain nuance that can seem impassable - just in physics (or mathematics etc), that wall is more visible. It is easier to tell that there is a lot you might not be getting. I’d say, explore anyway. Explore broadly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="self-education"/><category term="expository"/><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Five simple tips for the layman who wants to understand mathematics, physics, or similarly technical fields.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Missing Linear Algebra for Pure Mathematics Course</title><link href="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/missing-linear-algebra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Missing Linear Algebra for Pure Mathematics Course"/><published>2025-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/missing-linear-algebra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leoa9001.github.io/blog/2025/missing-linear-algebra/"><![CDATA[\[\def\ev{\mathrm{ev}} \def\span#1{\operatorname{span}\{#1\}} \def\Hom{\operatorname{Hom}}\] <p>Linear algebra is perhaps the most important field in mathematics (pure and applied). Much of the game of mathematics is reducing your problem to some linear algebra - likely a system of equations - and then solving it there. Entire subfields of mathematics could be characterized as generalizations of linear algebra concepts: Representation theory generalizes eigenspace decomposition, homological algebra generalizes the rank-nullity theorem, functional analysis is characterized as infinite-dimensional linear algebra. Considering all this, motivating a new treatise on the subject isn’t hard at all. However, claiming that the entire literature is missing a linear algebra treatment fit for pure mathematics is harder.</p> <p>The two canonical treatments of linear algebra are typified by Gilbert Strang’s <a href="https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/18-06-linear-algebra-spring-2010/">18.06</a> on MIT OCW, and Sheldon Axler’s <a href="https://linear.axler.net/">Linear Algebra Done Right</a> textbook. Strang’s treatment looks like most treatment of linear algebra. It works entirely in coordinates dealing with operations on row/column vectors and matrices. Axler’s treatment introduces abstract vector spaces and linear maps. Both work over fields $F = \mathbb{R}, \mathbb{C}$.</p> <p>One might think that this is <em>already</em> a sufficient treatment. Strang’s course represents the treatment given to all STEM students with a more applied flavor. Axler’s is the more abstract treatment that only the pure math students get. However, as a pure math student who learned from both Strang’s and Axler’s approaches, I was continually struck by how different linear algebra was in more advanced courses I took. I would have to pick up tidbits like working over finite fields, $\Hom (V,W)\simeq V^\ast\otimes W$, and trace being the composition $\Hom (V,V)\simeq V^\ast\otimes V \xrightarrow{\ev} F$. Constructions like the tensor product, symmetric product, and anti-symmetric product were also omitted. Similarly, what about tensor up restriction of scalars adjunction?</p> <p>Truthfully, the problem with Strang and Axler is that they did not teach linear algebra in the language that you see it in pure mathematics today. In Axler’s introduction, he bills his book as a second treatment in linear algebra that “<em>will focus on abstract vector spaces and linear maps.</em>” The course I am picturing would focus on operations on vector spaces in a <em>category of vector spaces</em>. That is, it would take the dual role of being the <strong>missing course on category theory</strong> too.</p> <p>In this respect, one could think of this as the third and final treatment of linear algebra: First Strang, then Axler, and finally this one. This would reflect how I learned linear algebra. Though I would want the text to be self-contained, like the Strang and Axler are, and I would picture it being a good <em>second</em> treatment of linear algebra. It would be good to have seen it before, whether from something like Strang or Axler.</p> <h2 id="how-the-course-or-book-would-be-differentstructured">How the course (or book) would be different/structured</h2> <p>The typical linear algebra course looks like this:</p> <ul> <li>Coordinate focused: row/column vectors and matrices</li> <li>All vector spaces are finite-dimensional</li> <li>Base-field $F = \mathbb{R}$ or $\mathbb{C}$</li> </ul> <p>This course would be rather different. First off</p> <h3 id="the-largely-coordinate-free-treatment">The largely coordinate-free treatment</h3> <p>It may come as a surprise to some, but all of the following can be defined without reference to a row/column vector or matrix:</p> <ul> <li>Vectors, Vector Spaces</li> <li>Bases, Rank</li> <li>Transpose, Adjoint</li> <li>Upper Triangular Matrices/Diagonal matrices</li> <li>Symmetric/Anti-symmetric matrices</li> <li>Inner Products</li> <li>Trace</li> <li>Determinant</li> <li>Tensors</li> <li>Eigenvectors, eigenvalues, eigenspaces</li> <li>Jordan Canonical Form</li> </ul> <p>Lets do a few examples now to illustrate: trace, transpose, upper triangular matrices, and Jordan Canonical form.</p> <p><strong>Trace and Transpose</strong>:</p> <p>The trace was mentioned earlier: there are a canonical map $V^\ast\otimes V\rightarrow \Hom_k(V,V)$ and $V^\ast \otimes V\rightarrow k$. The first is given by sending a dual-vector, vector pair $\phi\otimes v$ to the linear map $w\mapsto \phi(w) v$, the latter by sending the pair $\phi\otimes v$ to $\phi(v)$. Doing the composition right one recovers the trace: \(\text{tr}: \Hom_k(V,V)\rightarrow V^\ast \otimes V\rightarrow k\)</p> <p>How about the transpose? Well the transpose is the functorial part of the dual vector. The dual-space is actually functorial. Given $V\xrightarrow{f} W$, one gets a map $W^\ast \xrightarrow{f^\ast} V^\ast$. If $W$ is finite-dimensional, we also have $W\simeq W^{\ast\ast}$ and using that isomorphism we know that $V^\ast\otimes W\simeq (W^\ast)^\ast\otimes V^\ast\simeq \Hom(W^\ast, V^\ast)$ and this isomorphism also yields the transpose.</p> <p><strong>Upper Triangular Matrices</strong>:</p> <p>Suppose we have a linear map $f\in \Hom_k(V,V)$, how would we express that this map is upper-triangularizable without talking about the matrix of $f$? Well, what does it mean to be upper triangular in a conceptual way? If we have matrix of a linear map and it is upper triangular, we know that the left-most column is an entry with a bunch of zeroes. This means the vector $(1,0,0,\ldots,0)^t$ is sent to $(a,0,0,\ldots,0)^t$ - it is an eigenvector. Moreover, if we let $V_1 = \text{Span}_k((1,0,0,\ldots,0)^t)$, this subspace of $V$ is preserved by the linear map $f$. Similarly, we know that $\text{Span}_k ((1,0,\ldots)^t, (0,1,0,\ldots)^t)$ is preserved. Lets call this subspace $V_2$. We find that a map is upper-triangularizable if there exists a sequence of vector subspaces</p> \[V_0\subset V_1\subset\cdots \subset V_n = V\] <p>such that $f$ preserves each $V_i$. Such a decomposition of a vector space is called a (complete) flag.</p> <p><strong>Jordan Canonical Form</strong></p> <p>Ahhh I’ve talked enough - just trust me on this one. The short is that you can decompose your space into $\bigoplus V_{\lambda_i}$ wherein $f-\lambda_i$ restricts is nilpotent on each $V_{\lambda_i}$. If one takes the subring $k[f]\subset \Hom_k(V,V)$, the max-spectrum will correspond to the different $V_{\lambda_i}$s.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="advanced-math"/><category term="math-education"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Talking about how we never cover linear algebra in the language it is used in high level pure mathematics.]]></summary></entry></feed>